בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody. בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf
is צט, tzaddi-tet, 99, we're a little behind, we pick up צח
עמוד ב tzaddi-chet amud bet at the two dots about ten lines
down in the medium-sized lines. חמץ שעבר עליו הפסח אמרינן ליה הרי
שלך לפניך. Chometz she-avar alav ha-Pesach amrinan lei harei she-le-fanecha. So if
somebody stole חמץ chometz and then פסח Pesach passed over and now
it's worthless, nevertheless since it's physically the same object, he can give
it back and say, I've returned the object, right? My obligation is
to return the object, והשיב את הגזילה אשר גזל, v'heshiv et ha-gezeilah
asher gazal, the primary obligation is not pay back the value of
the object, the primary obligation is return the object, and the חידוש
chiddush of the משנה mishna is that one fulfills that obligation even
if the object is worthless if physically it's the same object, חמץ
שעבר עליו הפסח. chometz she-avar alav ha-Pesach. So the גמרא gemara says,
מאן תנא אומר באיסורי הנאה הרי שלך לפניך? man tana omer be-isurai
hana'ah harei she-le-fanecha? Who's the one that says that even when something
is forbidden in benefit and completely worthless, it's still you're still able
to say behold your thing is before you, that's considered to be
a legitimate returning of the object? אמר רב חסדא רבי יעקב היא,
Amar Rav Chisda Rabbi Yaakov hi, it's רבי יעקב. Rabbi Yaakov. דתניא,
Datanya, for we learned in a ברייתא, brayta, שור שהמית, shor she-heimis,
if an ox killed somebody, עד שלא נגמר דינו, ad she-lo nigmar
dino, before the גמר דין gmar din and before it had officially
the status of a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, מכרו מכור, machro machur,
if you sell it it's a good sale and as רש״י Rashi
points out and then once you did that it can't become a
שור הנסקל shor haniskal because it has to be under the same
ownership in order to make it into a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal,
הקדשו מוקדש, hekdesho mukdash, if you sanctify it it's sanctified, שחטו בשרו
מותר, shachato basaro mutar,
the meat is מותר mutar because it does not have a status
of a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, so you can sort of jump
in there and do these things before it gets that status and
then it won't become a שור הנסקל shor haniskal either. החזירו שומר
לבעליו, Hechziro shomer le-be'alav, now if somebody was given an ox to
watch and it became a שור הנסקל shor haniskal in the house
of the שומר, shomer, then if he returns it before גמר דין,
gmar din, before it has official status of a שור הנסקל, shor
haniskal, before then, it's a good
returning, מוחזר. mukhzar. משנגמר דינו, Mi-she-nigmar dino, however once there's been a
גמר דין gmar din and it has that status, so then it's
איסורי הנאה, isurai hana'ah, so מכרו אינו מכור, machro eino machur, you
can't do a good sale, you can't sell it, you no longer
have control over it, even if it's yours, הקדשו אינו מוקדש, hekdesho
eino mukdash, you can't sanctify it, שחטו בשרו אסור, shachato basaro asur,
once you slaughter the meat is אסור asur even if it wasn't
stoned, once it becomes meat the meat is אסור. asur. And
החזירו שומר לבעליו אינו מוחזר hechziro shomer le-be'alav eino mukhzar and if
you try to return it to the owner and say look see
I'm giving you back your ox, that's not legitimate, it's worthless, it's
not a legitimate returning of the object, okay? So that says you
cannot say הרי שלך לפניך harei she-le-fanecha by איסורי הנאה. isurai hana'ah.
רבי יעקב אומר אף משנגמר דינו החזירו שומר לבעליו מוחזר. Rabbi Yaakov
omer af mi-she-nigmar dino hechziro shomer le-be'alav mukhzar. No,
you can do it even after גמר דין, gmar din, you can
return it. So גמרא gemara says look, it looks like there's a
debate of תנאים tanaim of whether you can say הרי שלך לפניך
harei she-le-fanecha by something that is forbidden in הנאה. hana'ah. מאי לאו
בהא קמיפלגי, Mai lav be-ha kamifligi, it seems like this is the
debate. רבי יעקב סבר אמרינן באיסורי הנאה הרי שלך לפניך ורבנן סברי
לא אמרינן באיסורי הנאה הרי שלך לפניך. Rabbi Yaakov savar amrinan bi-surai
hana'ah harei she-le-fanecha ve-rabbanan savri lo amrinan bi-surai hana'ah harei she-le-fanecha.
Presumably the same way they debate by the שור הנסקל shor haniskal
they would debate by חמץ הפסח. chometz ha-Pesach. If something is physically
the same but it's אסור בהנאה, asur be-hana'ah, can you return it
and satisfy your obligation whether you are a גזלן gazlan or a
שומר shomer to say I've returned the object to the owner? So
isn't this the same debate and wouldn't they debate the case of
our משנה mishna of חמץ chometz as well? So the גמרא gemara
says, אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava says back,
לאו, lav, no, that's not the same debate. דכולי עלמא אמרינן באיסורי
הנאה הרי שלך לפניך, De-kulei alma amrinan bi-surai hana'ah harei she-le-fanecha, that
you
can say הרי שלך לפניך, harei she-le-fanecha, that's the general rule is
you can. And because if דאם
כן,
de-im
ken,
because if that weren't true, if they were to really be debating
whether you can say הרי שלך לפניך harei she-le-fanecha by איסורי הנאה,
isurai hana'ah, ניפלגו בחמץ הפסח. niflgu be-chometz ha-Pesach. Why are they debating
the שור הנסקל? shor haniskal? They should debate חמץ הפסח. chometz ha-Pesach.
Now you'd say what difference does it make, one or the other?
But we're going to see in a minute that the שור הנסקל
shor haniskal introduces other complications. So the fact that they only debated
the שור הנסקל shor haniskal and they didn't debate חמץ הפסח chometz
ha-Pesach shows says רבא Rava that in principle everybody agrees that you
can say הרי שלך לפניך harei she-le-fanecha and there are special considerations
by the שור הנסקל. shor haniskal. What are the special considerations by
the שור הנסקל? shor haniskal? אלא אמר רבא הכא בגומרין דינו של
שור שלא בפניו קמיפלגי. Ela amar Rava hacha be-gomrin dino shel shor
she-lo be-fanav kamifligi.
The question is whether you can have a גמר דין gmar din
of the ox not in the presence of the ox, okay? That's
the issue. How does that tie in here? בגומרין דינו של שור
שלא בפניו קמיפלגי. Be-gomrin dino shel shor she-lo be-fanav kamifligi. רבנן סברי
Rabbanan savri the Rabbis hold אין גומרין דינו של שור שלא בפניו,
ein gomrin dino shel shor she-lo be-fanav, that the בית דין beis
din can never have had the גמר דין gmar din without having
had the ox present.
So therefore what? That's why the שומר shomer can't return it. Why?
How does that tie in? דאמר ליה De-amar lei because they can
now say to the שומר shomer listen buddy, אי אייתיתיה ניהלי, ee
i-isat lei i-halai, if you would have returned it to me before
the גמר דין, gmar din, הרי מברחינא ליה לאגמא, harei mavrikna lei
le-agma,
I would have hidden it away in the אגמא agma swamp. השתא
Hasha now your negligence that you let בית דין beis din see
it, מסרתיה ביד מאן דלא מצינא לאשתעויי דינא בהדיה. masartei be-yad man
de-lo matzina l'ishtoyu dina bahadei. You've now had it seized by somebody
I cannot deal with, I cannot you know bring them to court
because they are the court. So basically it's your negligence that brought
this about and that's why you can't return it. רבי יעקב סבר
Rabbi Yaakov savar no, גומרין דינו של שור שלא בפניו. gomrin dino
shel shor she-lo be-fanav. בית דין Beis Din could have had the
גמר דין gmar din even without the ox present, דאמר ליה מאי
עבדי ליה, D'amar lei mai avdi lei, because you know, because you
know, because they say what have I done to you? סוף סוף
לא גמרו ליה דינא שלא בפניו, Sof sof lo gamru lei dina
shelo befanav, and even if I had returned it they would've had
a גמר דין. gmar din. So therefore in principle you can say
הרי שלך לפניך, harei shelcha lifanecha, the reason the רבנן Rabbanan say
you cannot here is because it was your negligence that this happened.
Now the obvious problem with this is, who cares that it was
your negligence that this happened? The whole idea is הרי שלך לפניך.
harei shelcha lifanecha. It doesn't, you know, it doesn't matter that it
was my negligence, it's the same object I'm returning. It was also
the גזלן's gazlan negligence that he didn't return the חמץ chametz before
פסח. Pesach. It was also the שומר's shomer negligence that maybe that
he let the שור shor become a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, that
he let the שור shor go out and gore. Right? So what
difference does this make if fundamentally you can say הרי שלך לפניך?
harei shelcha lifanecha? This is discussed by רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos
earlier because you might remember this came up much earlier. And תוספות
Tosafos basically tries to say that it's sort of like remember what
we discussed earlier
about פסולתו מלכות, psulto malchus, that if something is פסול passul by
the government, by the entire country, whatever, then it could be considered
like a visible damage even though physically the thing hasn't changed. But
if it changes the way we look at it, it's like it's
a visible damage. So תוספות Tosafos says the same issue is here
true by the case of the שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, that if
the reason is that בית דין Beis Din because they seized it,
that allowed it to become שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, so the fact
that it's being held by בית דין Beis Din and that was
sort of like critical to its status, that makes it like its
status of the שור הנסקל shor haniskal is visible. We see that
בית דין Beis Din is holding it, that's a part of it,
a necessary part of it becoming a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, so
somehow that makes it as if it's a visible status. That's the
way תוספות Tosafos explains it. רש"י Rashi tries to say there's some
combination of negligence and a non-visible damage that makes it impossible to
return, which is more פשט pshat of the words of the גמרא
Gmara but harder to understand. Anyway, that's the way the גמרא Gmara
is saying it. It's not so clear why that should matter, but
the גמרא Gmara is saying it's a unique issue by שור הנסקל
shor haniskal and the degree of negligence and degree of visibility over
the fact that בית דין Beis Din seized it. Okay, but it
would not be a debate by חמץ בפסח. chametz be'Pesach. Now let's
finish up this. Okay, so the גמרא Gmara says, אשכחיה רב חסדא
לרבה. Ashchei Rav Chisda l'Rabba. So
רב חסדא Rav Chisda found רבה בר שמואל. Rabba bar Shmuel. אמר
ליה תניתא מידי באיסורי הנאה. Amlei tanisa midi bisurei hana'ah. So רב
חסדא Rav Chisda was the one who wanted to say it was
the same debate. So he said to רבה בר שמואל, Rabba bar
Shmuel, have you taught any ברייתא Braisa about איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah
that could help us figure out whether this is the same debate
by שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, would they also debate חמץ בפסח chametz
be'Pesach or is it a local, a specific debate of שור הנסקל?
shor haniskal? אמר ליה, Amlei in, yes, I did teach something. תנינא,
Tanina, we taught: והשיב את הגזלה. V'heshiv es hagezeila. It says you
shall return the stolen object. מה תלמוד לומר Mah talmud lomar אשר
גזל, asher gazal, that you stole? יחזיר כעין שגזל. Yachzir k'ein shegazal.
So you have to return it in the state it was when
you took it. Okay? מכאן, Mikan, and otherwise it wouldn't be a
good returning. So what's defined as being in the same state? So
מכאן אמרו Mikan amru גזל מטבע ונפסל. gazal matbe'a venifsal. So this
is like a recap of our משנה. Mishnah. Okay? פירות והרקיבו, Peiros
vehirkivu, יין והחמיץ. yayin vehichmitz. So if you stole a
coin and it became invalid, fruit and they rotted, wine, now all
these by the way are going to be able to say הרי
שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lifanecha. So the גמרא's Gmara going to ask
about the rotting fruit because in our משנה Mishnah the rotting fruit
you were not able to say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lifanecha.
But here the גירסא girsa by והרקיבו, vehirkivu, most people here have
the גירסא girsa either והנתנסך, v'henitnasach, it was poured as יין נסך,
yayin nesech, so it's worthless but it's not visible. Or some have
the גירסא girsa of not והחמיץ vehichmitz but והקרים, v'hikrim, which means
that it became like a little bad but not really vinegary. Okay,
so it's a slight, so let's do the case והנתנסך. v'henitnasach. Okay,
so it was poured as יין נסך, yayin nesech, it's not visible.
תרומה ונטמאת, Terumah venitmeis, תרומה's terumah טמא. tamei. So somehow, so we
have mostly non-visible things here other than the fruit, right? The coin
is no longer valid, the wine is איסור הנאה, issur hana'ah, the
תרומה's terumah טמא, tamei, חמץ שעבר עליו הפסח, chametz she'avar alav haPesach,
בהמה ונעבדה בה עבירה, behemah vene'evda bah aveirah, an animal that was
used in an act of sex and now it has to be
either stoned or isn't good for the altar, ושור עד שלא נגמר
דינו, v'shor ad shelo nigmar dino, or an ox before the גמר
דין. gmar din. אומר הרי שלך לפניך. amner harei shelcha lifanecha. You
can say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lifanecha. All of that satisfies
the Torah's requirement of אשר גזל. asher gazal. Since it's physically the
same thing, it satisfies the Torah's requirement even though it's worth nothing.
Now, thing is, notice what this משנה Mishnah did. It said you
can say הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lifanecha by חמץ, chametz, but
you can only say it by the שור הנסקל shor haniskal before
גמר דין, gmar din, not after גמר דין, gmar din, which makes
it clear that the גמר דין gmar din of a שור הנסקל
shor haniskal is a separate consideration from the standard ability to say
הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lifanecha by איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah.
And other
things here you're able to say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lifanecha.
מאן חמית ליה דאמר עד שלא נגמר אין משנגמר לא? Man chamis
lei d'amar ad shelo nigmar in, mishenigmar lo? Who says you can
only return a שור הנסקל shor haniskal before גמר דין gmar din
and not after גמר דין? gmar din? רבנן, Rabbanan, the Rabbis. Right?
They're the ones who debate רב יעקב. Rav Yaakov. And even though
they're saying by a שור הנסקל shor haniskal you can't return it
after גמר דין, gmar din, דקתני, d'katni, it's we still teach חמץ
שעבר עליו הפסח chametz she'avar alav haPesach אומר הרי שלך לפניך. omer
harei shelcha lifanecha. You can say הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lifanecha
by חמץ. chametz. Who says you can only return a שור הנסקל
Shor HaNiskal before גמר דין Gmar Din and not after גמר דין?
Gmar Din? רבנן, Rabbanan, the Rabbis, right? They're the ones who debate
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. And even though they're saying by a שור
הנסקל Shor HaNiskal you can't return it after גמר דין, Gmar Din,
והתניא, v'hatanya, we still teach חמץ ועבר עליו הפסח אומר לו הרי
שלך לפניך. chametz ve'avar alav haPesach omer lo harei shelcha lefanecha. You
can say הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lefanecha by חמץ. chametz. You
can say it in general by איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. It's just
a special thing by a שור הנסקל Shor HaNiskal you can't say
it. So it shows that רבא Rava was right and רב חסדא
Rav Chisda was wrong. It's only a debate of שור הנסקל. Shor
HaNiskal. In general, you're able to say it. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
so רב חסדא Rav Chisda said: אי משכחו להו, ei mashkechu lehu,
if you see other people from the בית המדרש, Beis Medrash, לא
תימרו להו ולא מידי. lo teimru lehu velo midi. Don't tell them
anything. Don't tell them that I've been proven wrong by this ברייתא.
Baraisa. Which raises interesting questions about intellectual honesty, right? Okay, I was
totally proven wrong, רבא Rava was proven right, the ברייתא Baraisa shows
it's only a debate of שור הנסקל, Shor HaNiskal, everybody agrees in
general you can say הרי שלך לפניך, harei shelcha lefanecha, but don't
go ahead and publicize the fact that I got it wrong. Yes?
Isn't there something fundamental here?
אדם המזיק, adam hamazik, yeah?
הוה אמינא ואברח ליה לאגמא? hava amina v'avrach lei l'agma? In other
words, this is a שור, shor, this שור shor murdered somebody, killed
somebody. Right. I'm supposed to bring it to בית דין. Beis Din.
I could have laundered the money. Instead of exposing the money, I
could have laundered it under offshore accounts.
Yeah, that's an interesting point, you know, like, you know, what type
of an איסור issur is there in subverting... I mean, there's two
aspects. One is exposing the public to a hazard, but, you know,
you could make other arguments about that. Maybe I would have killed
it myself and eaten the meat, but I wouldn't have made it
into a שור הנסקל. Shor HaNiskal. The other is just like subverting
the justice of the court, right? Like, what type of a, you
know, what type, right, what type of an איסור issur is there?
One imagines there would be an איסור, issur, like there's an איסור
issur to not testify if you know testimony. There's an איסור issur
to testify falsely, right? But what type of an איסור issur is
there to like avoid the judgment of the court, especially if it's
not in terms of your liability to another person, you know?
It's a good question. On the other hand, let's remember that when
it comes to executing human beings, right, you know, רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says, if we were in the
court, we would have ensured that they never would have executed anybody,
we would have always found some loophole. So I understand this is
an ox and not a human being, but it raises interesting questions
about subverting the judgment of a court when it's basically between the
person and God, if you would, not between an interpersonal matter.
With the death of someone.
The death, yes. Good question, though, that the גמרא Gemara is never,
right, is never critical of that type of a, you know, it
never voices a problem with that type of a choice. Okay, let's
look at the next משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so that was the idea
about... so that was continuing until now we've been continuing the theme
of the first משנה, Mishnah, which is you pay כשעת הגזלה. keshas
hagezeilah. What's considered a שינוי shinui that you acquire it? What's not
enough of a שינוי shinui that maybe you don't acquire it but
it's damaged you have to pay the difference between its value now
and שעת הגזלה? shas hagezeilah? And when is it might be worth
nothing but it's physically the same and you can say הרי שלך
לפניך? harei shelcha lefanecha? Now
we turn a little bit away from גזילה, gezeilah, okay? And we
turn to an interesting question which maybe to some degree belongs more
in the first half of בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, which is if
a, if somebody that, a
craftsman or a, you know, somebody you've been given to do a
job with your object messes it up and damages the object. So
let's take a look. נתן לאומנין לתקן וקלקלו. Nasan l'umnin l'saken vekilkelu.
You gave some, you know, something to a, you know, you gave
your bike to the repair shop and they to fix
it and they messed it up, they ruined
the gears or
whatever
they did. חייבין לשלם. Chayavin l'shalem. They
have to pay, okay? נתן לחרש שידה
תיבה ומגדל.
Nasan l'charash shidah teivah
umigdal.
If you gave it to
a carpenter, a box and different
types of a box, a cabinet
or something
like that... חרש, charash, excuse me, right.
'Cause I see חרש cheresh I'm thinking... and then the next word
begins with a ש, shin, I'm thinking about saying חרש שוטה וקטן.
cheresh shoteh vekatan. Right. חרש, charash, thank you very much. Okay, נתן
לחרש, nasan l'charash, thank you. You gave to a carpenter, שידה תיבה
ומגדל, shidah teivah umigdal, some type of a box or cabinet לתקן,
l'saken, to fix, וקלקל, vekilkel, and they broke it, חייב לשלם, chayav
l'shalem, they have to pay. They're just like a basically like a
type of an אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. We'll discuss to what degree
it's אדם המזיק adam hamazik or a different category. והבנאי, V'habannai, and
let's say a builder, a construction guy, שקיבל עליו לסתור את הכותל,
shekibel alav listor es hakosel, that he took a, you know, he
took a commission to knock down a wall, ושיבר האבנים, veshiber ha'avanim,
and in the process he destroyed the stones, 'cause you want him
to dismantle the wall and use the stones elsewhere, and in the
process he actually broke the stones, או שהזיק, o shehizik, or he
damaged them, חייב לשלם, chayav l'shalem, he has to pay. הסותר מצד
זה ונפל מצד אחר. Hasoser mitzad zeh venafal mitzad acher. He was
remove... taking down the stones from one side of the wall and
because of what he was doing on the wall, some stones in
a different location of the wall fell down. פטור, Patur, he's exempt.
ואם מחמת המכה, Ve'im machmas hamakah, but if it's because of what
he did, he's hitting the wall with his hammer and that caused
the vibration, then חייב, chayav, then he does have to pay. Okay,
so all... so it's interesting what this is doing in our פרק.
perek. But anyway, we'll bracket that for a moment. Let's see what
the גמרא Gemara discusses. This gets us back to interesting אדם המזיק
adam hamazik discussions. The same way yesterday with all of רבה's Raba
statements about גרמא grama and throwing a coin into the ocean or
whatever, that got us back to אדם המזיק adam hamazik as well.
Here too we're revisiting an אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. אמר רב אסי,
Amar Rav Assi, says רב אסי: Rav Assi: לא שנו אלא שנתן
לחרש שידה תיבה ומגדל לנעוץ בה מסמר ונעץ בה מסמר. Lo shanu
ela shenasan l'charash shidah teivah umigdal lino'atz bah masmer vena'atz bah masmer.
ושיברן. v'shibran. The case is you gave them a box or whatever
cabinet to bang a nail into it, and in the process of
banging the nail they broke it, but meaning they didn't improve it
first, all they did was they ruined it in the process. Okay,
אבל aval נתן לחרש natan l'cheresh עצים eitzim לעשות la'asot שידה תיבה
ומגדל. shidah teivah umigdal. You gave them just wood and you said
build me a cabinet. ועשה מהם ve'asah mehem שידה תיבה ומגדל. shidah
teivah umigdal. And they built you a nice box, a nice cabinet,
ושיברן פטור. v'shibran patur. Now they built it, so here's the thing.
You gave them wood worth $20 and you said build me a
box. It's a gorgeous box worth $200. Banging in the next last
nail, they crashed the box and they broke it. What do they
owe you? Do they owe you the $20 for the wood or
do they owe you the $200 for breaking your beautiful box? Okay,
I'm going to pay you for, you know, for, you know, for
whatever the fee we agreed upon, but now it was my $200
box that you broke. Okay, so before the box is returned, the
craftsman put in this value, transformed the value. Who owns the box,
the improved value of the box, before it's been returned?
That's like stealing something and doing a שינוי shinnui to it.
Did he steal it? Is it yours yet?
It seems to be parallel, right? You had these raw materials and
you did a שינוי. shinnui.
Yeah, okay, it's somewhat similar, but even if there's not—yes, but I
don't—it's—we'll see how the גמרא Gemara says it. It's more like he's
created something. It's not like he—yes, it's true, he did change the
word from one to the other, but the question is less did
he own the wood because he changed it. The question is more
does he own, you know, his creation. Right. You know, so,
let's take a look. אבל נתן לחרש עצים לעשות מהם שידה תיבה
ומגדל ועשה מהם שידה תיבה ומגדל ושיברן פטור. Aval natan l'cheresh eitzim
la'asot mehem shidah teivah umigdal ve'asah mehem shidah teivah umigdal v'shibran patur.
You do not have to pay for breaking this $200 box. Okay,
you have to pay maybe for the wood or something. מאי טעמא?
Mai ta'ama? What's the reason? אומן קונה בשבח
כלי. Uman koneh b'shevach k'li. The craftsman owns the improvement of the
vessel until the time that he actually gives it back to the
owner. And by the way, the way that we're going to see
later the גמרא Gemara understands this is, if you give me 50
bucks to turn your wood into a box, according to this concept,
what you're really doing is saying, I will pay you $50 for
the box that you create. You're not paying me $50 for my
labor; you're—we've agreed that you're going to—I'm going to make a box
out of this and we've agreed that the selling point of that
box is going to be $50 and you're going to buy that
box off of me, but it's going to be my box until
I sell it to you. Yes.
So then why did you say that you would still pay them
for their labor? Seems like if they own the box and you're
getting the box now because it's broken, why are you paying them
money?
Well, if we would say that I'm not קונה בשבח כלי, koneh
b'shevach k'li, if we were to say it's your thing, so if
you're going to make me pay because it was your box and
I broke it, but it only became your box because you hired
me to make it—like you can't have both. You can't have not
paying me and it all, right, you know, and it have been—if
you weren't paying me, then I wasn't working for you when I
built the box, right?
Right, so you'd still be damaging my wood.
Okay, I would have to pay you for your wood, but you—but
if you want to collect for me destroying your $200 box, that
would only be if you actually paid me for the job, then
it became your $200, whatever.
Okay, but if we're saying that I'm paying that $200, you're
just—right, if you're right, if I'm not paying the $200, if I'm
then then I guess it—you're not paying for my labor. Right, exactly,
exactly. Okay, correct.
Right, because according to the conception that אומן קונה בשבח כלי, uman
koneh b'shevach k'li, you only anyway pay me—you're not paying me for
my labor, you're paying me to buy the box, right.
To buy—so if I bring an auto mechanic my broken car, so
I—and he charges me
$1,000, I'm buying back according to this a different car. Right, essentially.
I mean, it's an interesting question about the stage between knocking in
a nail and raw materials. Like if you're fixing something that's broken,
is that also שבח כלי? shevach k'li? Okay, but it's—let's take a
look. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, but it
really is a question of whether you conceptualize this as I'm paying
you for your labor and it's obviously my thing that now is
worth more that you're improving, which is the natural way of thinking
about it, or
we're agreeing on a new—on a purchase point of something that you're
going to create and you're going to own with my wood.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, מאי טעמא אומן
קונה בשבח כלי. mai ta'ama uman koneh b'shevach k'li. תנן, Tnan,
now let's look, our משנה Mishna says, נתן לאומנין וקלקלו חייבין לשלם.
natan l'umnin v'kilkelu chayavin l'shalem. You gave it to the craftsmen and
they destroyed it, they have to pay. מאי לאו דיהיב להו עצים,
mai lav d'yahiv lehu eitzim, so presumably it's that they gave him
wood and that's the חידוש chiddush of the משנה, Mishna, that they
have to pay for breaking a beautiful box even though it was
the box that they built. So גמרא Gemara says, לא, lo, no,
שידה תיבה ומגדל, shidah teivah umigdal, no, you gave them just a
box to bang a nail into, but if you gave them wood,
they would not have to pay. גמרא Gemara says, one minute, הא
מדקתני סיפא שידה תיבה ומגדל מכלל דרישא עצים. ha midkatni seifa shidah
teivah umigdal miklal d'reisha eitzim. No, there's two cases. First it says
you gave craftsmen, and then it says you gave him שידה תיבה
ומגדל. shidah teivah umigdal. So presumably the first case is you gave
him raw material and nevertheless it's your box that's being broken. So
גמרא Gemara says, no, אמר, amar, you can say... פירושא קמפרש לה.
perusha k'mefarash lah. The end part of the משנה Mishna is explaining
the first part. כיצד נתן לו לתקן וקלקל חייב לשלם. keitzad nasan
lo l'taken v'kilkal chayav l'shalem. Under what circumstances do they have to
pay for destroying the whole beautiful box? כגון שנתן לחרש שידה תיבה
ומגדל. k'gon she'nasan l'charash shida teiva umigdal. It's like you gave him
a box to begin with and they just were fixing it. But
if they built it from raw materials, they would not have to
pay. והכי נמי מסתברא דכיצד קתני. v'hachi nami mistavra d'keitzad katani. It
makes sense to read the משנה Mishna that the second case of
actually giving them a box is a clarification of the first line.
דאי סלקא דעתך רישא עצים, d'ei salka daitach reisha etzim, if the
first line was talking about giving them raw materials, wood, השתא שמעינן
עצים חייב לשלם, hashta shamainan etzim chayav l'shalem, you're going to tell
me that by raw materials you have to pay for destroying the
whole box? ולא אמרינן אומן קונה בשבח כלי v'lo amrinan uman koneh
b'shvach kli and we wouldn't say that the אומן uman takes possession
of the improvement, that it's my the
owner's thing that's now been improved. So that's true, שידה תיבה ומגדל
מיבעיא? shida teiva umigdal mibaya? Do you have to tell me that
you're paying if you break it when you got it whole, when
you already got it as a cabinet? No, אי משום הא לא
איריא. ei mishum ha lo irya. If that was your only point,
that's not it. תנא סיפא לגלויי רישא. tana seifa l'giluyei reisha. The
second case
is making it clear what the first case is talking about. שלא
תאמר, shelo tomar, you shouldn't say רישא שידה תיבה ומגדל אבל עצים
לא. reisha shida teiva umigdal aval etzim lo. You shouldn't think that
the first case, only because it's generic, נתן לאומנין, nasan l'ummanin, don't
think it's only talking about giving them a box, but if you
gave them raw material you would not have to pay for destroying
the finished product. תנא סיפא שידה תיבה ומגדל. tana seifa shida teiva
umigdal. So in the end it clarifies: we're not talking about giving
it raw material. Let me be clear. All we're talking about is
when you're giving them the already-built box.
דרישא עצים. d'reisha etzim. I got lost which way I was going.
First the גמרא Gemara is saying, oh, I'm sorry, first the גמרא
Gemara is saying what? First the גמרא Gemara is saying is the
second part is clarifying the first part because if the first part
were עצים, etzim, you wouldn't have to say the second part. And
then the גמרא Gemara is saying: no, the first part is עצים,
etzim, but had we not said the second part, you would have
said the first part was only a box. So therefore we say
that the second part is a box, מכלל, michlal, to make it
clear דרישא עצים d'reisha etzim that the first part is talking about
wood, ואפילו הכי חייב לשלם, v'afilu hachi chayav l'shalem, and even so
you have to pay. Alright, so one way or the other, it's
not clear if the משנה, Mishna, if the first part, the second
part of the משנה Mishna is clearly talking about the box, is
the first part of the משנה Mishna just a lead-in to that,
or is the first part of the משנה Mishna talking about raw
material? So you can't prove from the משנה Mishna this question of
whether if you give the craftsman the raw material and they build
a box, do they own that box now or do you own
that box? And if they destroy it, do they have to pay
you for destroying your box, or do they just have to pay
you for your wood? Okay. לימא מסייע ליה? leima msaya lei? Let's
try to prove this idea of אומן קונה בשבח כלי. uman koneh
b'shvach kli. הנותן צמר לצבע. hanosen tzemar l'tzaba.
You gave wool to a dyer. והקדיחה יורה v'hikdicha yora
and the pot caused it to burn and destroy. Meaning it's not
like he did anything wrong, whatever, but whatever, it just got destroyed
in the process.
He did something wrong, maybe he didn't watch it. נותן לו דמי
צמרו. nosen lo d'mei tzamro. He pays you for your wool. Okay,
דמי צמרו d'mei tzamro in, the cost of the wool, yes. דמי
צמרו ושבחו לא? d'mei tzamro v'shivcho lo? Why doesn't he pay you
for destroying dyed wool? Because maybe presumably first it got dyed and
it got improved in value and then it got destroyed. So דמי
צמרו d'mei tzamro in, the cost of the wool, yes, דמי צמרו
ושבחו לא, d'mei tzamro v'shivcho lo, he doesn't pay you for having
destroyed your improved wool. So לאו, lav, are we not talking about
a case שהקדיחה לאחר נפילה she'hikdicha l'achar nefilla that first it fell
into the pot, it absorbed the dye, and then it got burnt
and then it got destroyed? And nevertheless he's not paying you for
the destroyed improved wool, דאיכא שבח, d'ika shvach, that it's a bit
improved? ושמע מינה אומן קונה בשבח כלי? ushma mina uman koneh b'shvach
kli? And we see that he owns the improvement because he's not
paying you for the improved wool, he's only paying you for the
base wool. אמר שמואל, amar Shmuel, no, הכא במאי עסקינן שהקדיחה בשעת
נפילה. hacha b'mai askinan she'hikdicha b'shas nefilla. No, who says? Maybe it
means that as soon as the wool fell in, it got
destroyed, דליכא שבח, d'leika shvach, that there was no improvement.
אבל הקדיחה לאחר נפילה מאי? aval hikdicha l'achar nefilla mai? So then
what would you say? You would say though that if he burnt
it after it absorbed the dye, what would be the story? נותן
לו דמי צמרו ושבחו. nosen lo d'mei tzamro v'shivcho. Then he would
pay for the wool and the improvement, he would pay for the
full value. So that's true, if that's what you, שמואל, Shmuel, are
saying, you're explaining this משנה Mishna to be it got destroyed right
away, implies that if it would have been destroyed after it improved,
that he would pay for the improved value. It implies that you,
שמואל, Shmuel, hold
that אומן uman is not קונה בשבח כלי. koneh b'shvach kli. If
he's going to pay for the improved value, he's not קונה בשבח
כלי, koneh b'shvach kli, right? You want to say that if it
would have improved first, you would have paid for the improved value.
למימרא, l'meimra, that that seems to indicate that שמואל לית ליה דרב
אסי. Shmuel leis lei d'Rav Assi. שמואל Shmuel would argue with רב
אסי. Rav Assi. שמואל Shmuel would say an אומן uman is not
קונה koneh and if he destroyed it later in the process he
pays for the full value.
אמר לך שמואל, amar lach Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel would say no, not
necessarily, maybe I do hold אומן קונה בשבח כלי. uman koneh b'shvach
kli. But הכא במאי עסקינן hacha bemai askinan כגון דצמר וסמנים דבעל
הבית. kegon detzemer vesimanim deba'al habayit. דצבע אגר ידיה הוא דשקיל. detzeva
agar yadeih hu deshakeil. There becomes an interesting question. If you say
that an אומן uman is קונה בשבח כלי, koneh beshvach kli, what
are the circumstances in which you frame it that way, or you
frame the guy is only paying you for your labor? There's got
to be ways in which you can pay the guy only for
his labor. So the גמרא Gemara says well let's say for example
you provide all the raw material. I provide the wool and I
provide the dye and all you have to do is you have
to like combine the two. So that case maybe you're seen as
just a hired hand and you're not like take possession of it.
Now I don't really get that fully because I can imagine you
give me what wool? That's pretty much all the raw materials and
the rest is just my skill. What if you give me wood
and nails and I turn it into a beautiful table? Since I
have you gave me the raw materials that's like what is the
point? I'm not exactly sure, right? Is it just cause you provided
the raw materials that changes it? I mean the גמרא Gemara is
going to describe in a minute a case where let me maybe
give you an easier contrast. A case where I'm not commissioning you
to build a table, I'm not commissioning you to dye the wool.
I am paying you an hourly wage, okay? You come in, obviously
the job is to get the table done, but at the end
of the day I'm just paying you by the hour. In that
case you're not אומן קונה בשבח כלי. uman koneh beshvach kli. You're
not creating something and I'm paying you for the end product. You
are just doing I'm paying you per hour for your working on
this job. Okay. So that you understand that even if אומן קונה
בשבח כלי uman koneh beshvach kli that you're not sort of producing
it and owning it and selling it to me, you're just being
paid by the hour. Somehow the גמרא Gemara understands at least in
the case of dyeing, and I don't know if it would say
this by all other things because presumably there are not too many
materials by the case of making the cabinet, right? But for the
case of dyeing it somehow assumes that if I give you the
wool and the dye then you're not being sort of paid for
the job and you're not sort of you know creating something new
and I'm buying something new off of you. Then because I also
gave you the dye I'm just paying you for your labor.
Because there's the יורה yoreh and there's the עצים etzim to heat
it up, right? There's all that stuff he's saying.
Well the גמרא Gemara speaks about the dye, doesn't speak about the
עצים, etzim, but anyway, but for some reason because I've also given
the dye that changes it from a case of create this thing
and I'll buy this thing off of you which is how you
would conceptualize it as אומן קונה בשבח כלי uman koneh beshvach kli
more like I'll pay you for your labor. Okay. But then again
maybe because the dye I don't know yeah you think you have
an idea Jenna why they I mean because think about the carpentry
case right? The wood is pretty much all the raw materials if
I also gave if I also threw in some nails that would
make the difference?
A carpenter when he when like he's going to come to a
job for you, he's going to bring his own nails, he's going
to bring his own tools, he's going to bring he's like a
professional who has like a setup whereas here you're just giving the
raw materials and he's bringing it into his kind of.
Yeah but isn't the isn't the dyer the same? Doesn't he have
his vat and his fire and everything?
And so if he doesn't have his own dye I mean well
I don't know I guess that is weird.
If you want to say if he if you have everything if
it's my dyeing operation and I just hire you, right but maybe
that's what the גמרא Gemara means by giving the dye, but it's
you're just giving me the dye. You say look I I went
to China, I bought this gorgeous dye, here's the dye, here's this
wool and I'm going to take it into my and you know
you're going to take it into your factory and do it. That
would I don't know. Maybe not, I don't know.
Okay so it's some kind of like toss over of a buyer?
Could be, you could be right. So for some reason that would
change the scenario. Other cases are going to be more obvious where
you're just being paid for your labor. Okay. בצבעא Betzava so in
that case that you're giving him the dye, the dyer, אגר ידיה
הוא דשקיל. agar yadeih hu deshakeil. He is just getting the the
you know the fee for his work, you know literally like the
שכר sechar of ידיו yadav you know the fee for his handiwork.
שכר ידיו. Sechar yadav.
אי הכי Ei hachi if that's true, נותן ליה דמי צמרו וסמניו
nosin leih dmei tzamro vesimanim בעי ליה. bayei lei. That can't be
because then if it's also your dye then it should have said
he has to reimburse you for the wool and for the dye,
not for the improved wool but at least for the cost of
the dye. That's clearly not the case. So then if the פסק
psak says that we're talking that it got destroyed right away, sounds
like שמואל Shmuel holds that if it improved it's not אומן uman
is not קונה בשבח כלי. koneh beshvach kli. אלא Ella but you
know what the גמרא Gemara says you can't pin שמואל Shmuel down.
He doesn't have a clear position on this. שמואל דחויי קמדחי ליה.
Shmuel dechuya kimidacha leih. He's just saying you can't prove anything from
that משנה. Mishnah. He says look I I don't know what I
hold about this or I'm not taking a side on this. I'm
just saying the משנה Mishnah that it says pay for the wool
you can't prove that an אומן uman is not קונה בשבח כלי
koneh beshvach kli because it could be talking about the fact that
it got destroyed right away. Okay, so we can't prove one way
or the other.
If I hire a house painter to paint the walls of my
house, the outside of my house, according to that he owns the
outside wall of my house?
No, so again I think that the גמרא Gemara like I said
went to extremes. It went from knocking in a nail to creating
יש מאין yesh mei'ayin from wood creating a box, right? If you
have a dented thing and they fix a damage I don't think
that's the שבח כלי. shvach kli. I think we really are talking
about something that has transformed. And in some way that makes it
more relevant for גוזל עצים gozel eitzim discussion, talking about like a
שינוי shinui transforms the identity of something. Right, but notice that's not
in the משנה. Mishna. That's the discussion in the גמרא. Gemara. All
the משנה Mishna says is that you pay for damages. Yes.
And in secular law, there's a concept of mechanics lien where if
I give you something to fix and you fix it, you don't
own it, but you have the right to keep
it until I pay you. That's a different story. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this, תא שמע, ta shma, come and hear.
הנותן טלית לאומן, Ha-nosein tallis lo-uman, you gave your cloak right to
the אומן. uman. גמרו והודיעו, Gamro v'hodio, so he finished it and
he let you know, 'Hey buddy, your shirt's ready to pick up.'
אפילו מכאן ועד עשרה ימים אינו עובר עליו. Afilu mikan v'ad asara
yamim eino over alav. Even if you wait ten days to pick
it up, or ten days is a whatever, it means like wait
a hundred days, you don't transgress the issue of the prohibition of
לא תלין פעולת שכיר אתך עד בוקר. lo salin pe'ulas sachir itcha
ad boker. Don't allow the fee
for the person that you hired to sleep over night. You have
to pay him within the next period immediately after the day of
work. So here you waited ten days to pay him. But the
חידוש chiddush here of this is that until you've picked it up,
you're not yet obligated to pay him. He might have done the
work, but your obligation to pay him does not begin until you
pick it up. Okay, so it's a focus on this question of
the איסור issur of לא תלין פעולת שכיר. lo salin pe'ulas sachir.
אינו עובר עליו, Eino over alav, you don't transgress משום לא תלין.
mishum lo salin. נתנו לו בחצי היום, Nasano lo b'chatzi hayom, if
he gave it to you in the middle of the day, he
gave it to you at 2:00 PM, כיון ששקעה החמה, keivan she-shaka
ha-chama, so
once now you have until the end of that period. If his
work finished at sunset, then you have the night to pay him.
If his work finished here in the middle of the day, you
have until sunset to pay him. So כיון ששקעה החמה עובר עליו
משום בל תלין. keivan she-shaka ha-chama over alav mishum bal talin. Okay,
now, but here's the question: why is that relevant to our discussion?
Here's why it's relevant. אי סלקא דעתך
אומן קונה בשבח כלי, Ei salka dach'tach uman koneh b'shevach kli, if
an אומן uman takes possession in the improvement, אמאי עובר משום בל
תלין? amai over mishum bal talin? Why do you transgress? You should
never transgress. Why should you never transgress? Because
it's never the fee of his handiwork; it's only a sale. Right,
even if he gives it to me, once he gives me my
shirt, I'm not holding back from him his fee, what I'm holding
back from him is the money of the sale. Right? Because the
transaction is conceptualized as a sale. You guys with me here? And
by the way, though, notice that this is a case of a
shirt to fix, not something from raw material creating a complete new
thing. So even in this case of fixing something, it's considered to
be it's now his new object, which is very funny. I mean,
what do you mean his new object? Like, you know, it's a
car that you took, 99 percent of that car is mine, like
what percent of it exactly do you own? You own the whole
car now? I mean, it's hard to exactly understand what is it
that he owns if he made a small fix
in something.
Why doesn't he over after ten days, but he is over after
a half a day?
Because until you pick it up, you're not obligated to pay.
Say it again.
Until you pick it up.
Right. Okay, but what the גמרא Gemara says is, if אומן קונה
בשבח כלי, uman koneh b'shevach kli, it's never his fee. It's always
just like I haven't paid you for a sale. If I buy
a car off of you and I'm taking my time paying you,
I'm not over
on לא תלין פעולת שכיר, lo salin pe'ulas sachir, I'm just late
in paying you for a sale. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
but again, the חידוש chiddush here is that the גמרא Gemara applies
it even to like fixing something. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
רב מרי בריה דרב כהנא, Amar Rav Mari brei d'Rav Kahana, בגרדי
דסרבלא. b'gardi d'sarvala. Okay, we're talking about a case of like some
of the woolly part of a thick cloth that you basically wanted
him to smooth it or something, דלית ליה שבחא. d'leis lei shevacha.
So the גמרא Gemara here is trying to describe the line of
when it's considered to be like you really changed the thing and
improved it that he now owns it. So you didn't really have
him fix like a torn garment, make it from a non-garment to
a garment, you just had him do some type of a trivial
type of a thing, smooth it down. The גמרא Gemara says, שורתא,
shurta, still an improvement, סוף סוף, sof sof, למאי יהביה ליה? l'mai
yahvei lei? Why do you give it to him? Obviously he was
fixing something, דריכא, d'reicha, to soften it. He did something and it
softened the hard wool. כיון דריכא היינו שבחא. Keivan d'reicha hainu shevacha.
That's the שבח. shevach. So he doesn't own and here by the
way is the answer to what we're talking about, it's not אומן
קונה בכלי, uman koneh b'kli, it's אומן קונה בשבח. uman koneh b'shevach.
Okay, so and this is why the גמרא Gemara can apply it
even to a small improvement. See, you tell him to fix your
Bentley's fender, he doesn't own your car, he owns the improvement of
your car. Your car was worth ten thousand dollars and now it's
worth eleven thousand dollars. So he owns that thousand dollar value in
your car. Your shirt, your hard shirt, was worth nine dollars. Now
that it's softer, it's worth ten dollars. He owns one dollar value
in your ten dollar shirt. So he is now he is selling
you. at a bargain rate of fifty cents because that's what you
agreed on, right? You told the mechanic I'll pay you $100 to
fix my fender. So he is selling you your improved $1,000 value
of your car for the low rate of $100. That's what you
agreed upon. Okay, but he doesn't own the car, he owns the
improved value of the car. Okay, so it's like an abstract type
of a thing, but we're still conceptualizing it as a sale and
not as a fee for services. Is this clear to everybody? This
is why you can apply conceptually אומן קונה בשבח כלי, Uman koneh
b'shevach kli, that's אומן קונה בשבח כלי. Uman koneh b'shevach kli.
So the mechanic, the guy does the improvement can't really make a
claim of ownership on the object.
Doesn't own the object, he owns a part of the object. He
owns the improved value of the
object, an aspect.
Yeah, the improved value of the object. But you, but but you
agreed that he would sell it to you at whatever price you
agreed at the beginning.
Ultimately contractual.
Yeah, but we're conceptualizing it as, we're conceptualizing it's a very abstract,
yeah, we're conceptualizing an idea of like a type of a commission
to improve an object, not as a payment for services, but as
a payment for what you've improved in the object. Like you know,
you owned that improvement and I'm going to buy it off of
you.
Yeah, and if you mentioned if you're still owning the bulk of
the car whatever you mentioned he would have to if you like
don't pick it up within the time frame that they said that
you would have to like pay rental fees in order to store
it, right?
Yeah, but that's, but that's true regardless, right? However you conceptualize it
that's true, right?
No, if they owned it.
Right, if they were to totally own it, but we're not, right,
but that's true, but we're not saying that, right.
Yeah, I understand the distinction, I just don't understand why we're choosing
to structure it like this.
Right, right, why are we structured like that? Everybody conceptualizes as a
fee as a type... now the reason might be, and this might
be what, again it's funny because the גמרא Gemara belongs in, in
this section of בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, the משנה Mishna didn't. The
משנה Mishna just says you have to pay for damages. But, but
what we're going here with אומן קונה בשבח כלי, Uman koneh b'shevach
kli, once we've established this whole idea of שינוי קונה, shinuy koneh,
which is what Rabbi Dov was saying, now you can understand an
idea that's saying, well one minute, then even if somebody, maybe if
somebody even more so if somebody is doing it with license to
do it, I mean not because he's working for you, he's like
an extension of you, but one way or the other, if he's
transforming it and making a שינוי shinuy of it, maybe that should
give him some ownership rights in it. So in a way based
on what we've discussed before about שינוי קונה, shinuy koneh, you understand
why it leads us to thinking maybe you actually own that thing
that you improved until you give it back to the owner. Right?
So sure, it is a sense, right.
But anyway, let's see where the גמרא Gemara now
continues. Okay, סוף סוף למאי יהבי ליה ולרכוכי תספיניה, Sof sof l'mai
yahavi lei u'l'ruchokei taspeinei, כיון דרכוכי תספיניה, keivan d'ruchokei taspeinei, היינו שבחא,
hainu shevacha, that's the improvement. So why again are you considered to
be a hired hand, you should be a seller and there should
be no איסור issur of לא תלין. lo talin. The גמרא Gemara
says, לא צריכא דאגריה לבטשא. Lo tzricha d'agrei l'vatsha. So you hired
him to like basically to stomp on it, maybe also as a
way of softening it. Now why does that make a difference? So
because you said בטשא בטשא במעתא, Batsha batsha b'mata, every stomping you
do I'll pay you a dollar. So דהיינו שכירות, de'hainu schirut, so
you're not paying him for the end result, you're not... he's not
a contractor, okay? He's a hired hand. Every hour you walk on
it,
you know, I want you to, you know, to run it through
the machines and I'll pay you a dollar for every time, you
know, you whatever, you do the stomping. So that's not paying for
the end result, that's clearly paying him as a hired hand. Okay,
מסייע ליה לרב ששת, Mesayei lei l'Rav Sheshet, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this, אמר ליה למאי דסלקא דעתך מעיקרא דלא אגריה לבטשא,
Amar lei l'mai d'salka da'tach mei'ikara d'lo agrei l'vatsha, what we thought
initially that you weren't paying him for the stomping and it wasn't
for you know, and he was actually a case of contracting, מסייע
ליה לרב ששת, mesayei lei l'Rav Sheshet, this supports
Rav Sheshet, דבעא מיניה רב ששת, deba'a minei Rav Sheshet, asked Rav
Sheshet about a question which really intersects with our question,
קבלנות, kablanut, if you hire somebody as a קבלן, kablan, as a
contractor for the job not hourly, עובר עליו משום בל תלין או
אינו עובר עליו, over alav mishum bal talin o eino over alav,
you transgress בל תלין bal talin or not? Okay, I'm paying you
$1,000 to whatever you know, to make me a cabinet, okay, and
then I delay paying you. To some degree the answer is well
if you say אומן קונה בשבח כלי, uman koneh b'shevach kli, then
it's not, then it's a purchase, right? So then you're not over
on בל תלין. bal talin. But Rav Sheshet asked this question without
the framing of אומן קונה בשבח כלי, uman koneh b'shevach kli, and
you could understand look the תורה Torah says פעולת שכיר, pe'ulat sachir,
a hired hand. So maybe just technically that's not the same for
somebody who's a קבלן. kablan. Forget אומן קונה בשבח כלי. uman koneh
b'shevach kli. So he wanted to know is there the איסור issur
by קבלנות. kablanut. Okay, ואמרו ליה לרב ששת, ve'amru lei l'Rav Sheshet,
they asked Rav Sheshet, and רב ששת Rav Sheshet said to them,
עובר, over, you do transgress, which sounds like not only is it
in the פסוק pasuk of לא תלין, lo talin, but that אומן
uman is not קונה בשבח כלי, koneh b'shevach kli, otherwise it would
be a sale. לימא דרב ששת פליגא דרב אסי, Leima d'Rav Sheshet
pliga d'Rav Assi, does that Rav Sheshet argues on Rav Assi and
says that an אומן uman is not קונה בשבח כלי? koneh b'shevach
kli? אמר שמואל בר אחא בשליחא דאיגרתא, Amar Shmuel bar Acha b'shlicha
d'igarta, no, no, no, because the way you could have a contractor
without שבח כלי. shvach kli. What could you have there? You hire
somebody to deliver a letter. Okay, so I'm paying you for the
job. I don't care if it takes you one hour or a
thousand hours. I'm paying you for the job of delivering the letter,
but there's no physical object that got improved as a result. It's
a service. It's a service. Exactly.
A service as opposed to manufacturing.
Yeah. Right. So if it is so we could have a case
where we could ask the question: if אומן uman is קונה בשבח
כלי, koneh be'shvach kli, then when you actually produce something new, make
an improvement, that would not be פעולת שכיר peulat sachir because that's
a sale. That's not a fee. Okay, but what רב ששת Rav
Sheshes wanted to know is a type of a קבלנות kablanut that
does not improve something. A service. I'm paying and I'm paying you
for the job. And in that type of a case, it's not
אומן קונה בשבח כלי, uman koneh be'shvach kli, but it's not exactly
שכר שכיר. sachar sachir. Is that in the category of לא תלין
פעולת שכיר? lo talin peulat sachir? And רב ששת Rav Sheshes said
that it was.
How about a service like psychotherapy?
There you go.
Fix the guy's nut.
No, that's hardly שבח כלי. shvach kli. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Go try
to get a psychiatrist to agree with that, to be based on
the end result, not on the process. Okay. Anyway, so now the
all
now the HMOs all pay capitation.
Okay. Anyway. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: לימא כתנאי. leima
kitana'i. Let's say that this is a debate of תנאים. tannaim. Okay,
of אומן קונה בשבח כלי. uman koneh be'shvach kli. A woman says
to a man, עשי לי שירים נזמים וטבעות, asei li shirim nezamim
vetaba'ot,
make for me, you know, here's some gold, make for me some
nice, you know, necklaces and nose rings and rings. וקדש לי בך.
vekadeish li bach. And you'll turn that into these nice pieces of
jewelry and I'll marry you with that, instead of giving me a
ring, by turning my gold into a ring, that will be the,
you know, כסף kesef that you've given me that I'll marry you.
Okay. כיון שעשאן מקודשת. keivan she'asan mekudeshet.
So once this guy's turned it into these nice jewelry, she's married
because he now presumably what did he give her? Presumably he gave
her the improved value of the gold, which would mean אומן uman
is not קונה בשבח כלי. koneh be'shvach kli. She gives him the
gold. She gave him the gold. And he turns it into the
jewelry. Oh, into a ring. Into a ring, right. So now so
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, דברי מאיר, divrei Meir, רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says she's מקודשת. mekudeshet. Presumably why? I just you know I
gave this woman something. I gave her the increased value of her
gold, which means אומן, uman, okay. So that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says. וחכמים אומרים, va'chachamim omrim, and the Rabbis say, אינה מקודשת,
einah mekudeshet, she's not married, עד שיהא ממון מידו, ad sheyehei mamon
miyado, until she gets money into her hands. מאי ממון? mai mamon?
Now what does it mean that she gets money? אילימא אותו ממון,
ilei'ima oto mamon, until those rings go into her hands? מכלל דרבי
מאיר סבר אותו ממון לא? mi'chlal de'Rabbi Meir savar oto mamon lo?
So what, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would hold that she's married even
before the rings have been handed over? So, that's אלא במאי מקדש
לה? ela b'mai mekadeish lah? What's he marrying her with? Okay, what
did he give her? Now I don't exactly get that because you
could say if an אומן uman is, you know, you could say
that, you know, he gave her the increased value even if he
hasn't physically handed it over yet. What?
Well how's he give it to her if he hasn't handed? Right.
Well he's improved her
I
guess
he's given her a
service that he kept her for himself so what? Right.
But he's קונה בשבח כלי, koneh be'shvach kli, he's
made the
ring, it's his, not hers. Right.
And then he can give it to her.
I don't know, let's say he never took possession. Let's say he
went and he works on her car and he said I'll marry
you with the work I'll do on your car and he basically
and the car was in her driveway. So then it never left
her. Yeah.
Or he never took it.
Oh, like on the car, he's fixing a fender.
Fixing the fender.
I don't know. Anyway, we'll go on. It sounds to me it's
not so clear why she has to have physical possession of the
object. Her object now, she's not selling the object. Her object now
has greater value. Why does why is it so clear to the
גמרא Gemara that she has to take physical possession of the object?
He's now increased the value of her property.
By a pro by a pro. Right. Anyway, but and whoever gets
betrothed today with money? Well, it's only an object.
Well, that's different. Okay. So now anyway but the גמרא Gemara understands
that until it's been handed over you can't say that he's given
her anything. Okay. So you can't say he's given her anything until
he's handed over. So אלא פשיטא מאי ממון ממון אחר? ela peshita
mai mamon mamon acher? Must be the Rabbis mean you'll never marry
her by giving her the improved rings. If you want to marry
her you have to give her something else. So now what are
they debating? וסברו, vesavru, and we're assuming, דכולי עלמא ישנו לשכירות מתחילה
ועד סוף. dechulei alma yeshnu l'schirus mitichilah ve'ad sof.
Here's another fun debate, which is: when you pay somebody for a
job, assume now אומן uman is not קונה בשבח כלי, koneh be'shvach
kli, I'm paying you for a job, okay, do I basically owe
you zero until you're done with the job? And when you're done
with the job I owe you whatever we agreed upon, a hundred
dollars.
Or every single minute you work, I owe you for, you know,
it's like accrued interest. Like for every single minute whatever. I owe
you for every minute that you work, you know, I owe you
a penny for every minute that you work. And then if you're
in the middle of the job I'll owe you for, you know,
at that stage I owe you fifty dollars. If it's three quarters
of the way I'll owe you seventy five dollars. End of the
day I'll owe you a hundred dollars. Do I owe you nothing
until the job is over? Okay. Yes, you had this before. So
ישנו לש yeshnu lise... everybody all And everybody else agrees המקדש במלווה
אינה מקודשת, Hamikadesh B'milveh Eina Mikudeshes, that if you try to marry
a woman with a debt, with money she owes you, or money
of you, but let's say money she owes you, she's not married
because you haven't given her anything. You're not marrying her with the
benefit of being מוחל Mochel the debt. Let's say she owes you
a hundred dollars and you're saying keep the hundred dollars, so you
haven't given her anything. Okay, so she's אינה מקודשת. Eina Mikudeshes. So,
if putting all that together, why is that relevant? So this woman
gave me this stuff. Okay. If
אין לשכירות אלא לבסוף, Ein Lis'chirus Ela L'vasof, so she owes me
nothing for my work, okay, until it's done. When it's done, that
would come with a charge of a hundred dollars, and at that
moment I'm saying I'm not paying you the hundred dollars, I'm giving
you my work, my labor I'm giving you. Okay, so in that
case it seems like I'm מקדש Mekadesh her with the value of
my labor, and that could work. But if ישנה לשכירות מתחילה ועד
סוף, Yeshna Lis'chirus Misatchala V'ad Sof, okay, every
as I'm working, it's money that she owes me. So by the
time I'm done, it's not like it's not like I'm rather than
owing me something, here's take the gift of my labor. No, as
I was working, she was owing me for every minute of work.
So right now all we have is a hundred dollar debt, right,
that's been accrued. So in that time if I want to say
don't pay me, what I'm really saying is I'm מקדש Mekadesh you
with the money you owe me, the מלווה, Milveh, the money that
you've been owing me since the beginning.
המקדש במלווה אינה מקודשת. Hamikadesh B'milveh Eina Mikudeshes. So number one, because
we say ישנה לשכירות מתחילה ועד סוף, Yeshna Lis'chirus Misatchala V'ad Sof,
what we have here created is a debt, is a מלווה. Milveh.
And therefore I can't marry her with the מלווה. Milveh. So what
can I marry her with? How can she be מקודשת Mikudeshes by
what I've done to improve the object? Let's take a look.
So,
מאי לאו באומן קונה בשבח כלי קמיפלגי? Mai Lav B'uman Koneh B'shvach
Kli Kamiflagi? Do they dispute whether אומן קונה בשבח כלי? Uman Koneh
B'shvach Kli? רבי מאיר סבר אומן קונה בשבח כלי ורבנן סברי אין
אומן קונה בשבח כלי. Rebbi Meir Savar Uman Koneh B'shvach Kli V'rabanan
Savri Ein Uman Koneh B'shvach Kli. So therefore רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
says, look, you're right. But
it's not that she owes me a hundred dollars. What's the reality
here that I've improved it? Not that she owes me a hundred
dollars, the reality is I now own a hundred you know the
improved value of these these gold. Now under other circumstances I would
have sold that for a hundred dollars, but but now I'm not
selling it to her, I'm saying I own the improved value of
your gold and I'm going to give you my portion in this
gold, in this jewelry, and you'll marry me with it. So then
you understand right away now I have to hand it over, right,
because it's my gold that I'm now handing over, my improved value.
That's what רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says.
Her gold is my her gold is my
jewelry. Exactly. Exactly. Exactly. רבנן סברי אין אומן קונה בשבח כלי. Rabanan
Savri Ein Uman Koneh B'shvach Kli. No, you don't own any part
of this jewelry. It's only a hundred dollars that's owed to you,
and you can't marry her with a debt. So that seems to
be the debate. הגמרא Ha'gemara says לא, Lo, not necessarily. דכולי עלמא
Dechulei Alma I'll tell you everybody
says דכולי
עלמא אין אומן קונה בשבח כלי.
Dechulei Alma
Ein Uman Koneh B'shvach Kli.
You don't own the שבח. Shevach. You only owe and it's really
she only owes you a hundred dollars. אלא הכא בישנה לשכירות מתחילה
ועד סוף קמיפלגי. Ela Hacha B'yeshna Lis'chirus Misatchala V'ad Sof Kamiflagi. The
debate is whether it's a debt that she's been owing you money,
the debt's been accruing, or whether it is you know only something
that comes at the end. רבי מאיר סבר אין לשכירות אלא לבסוף.
Rebbi Meir Savar Ein Lis'chirus Ela L'vasof. The fee only comes at
the end. Until then she owes you nothing. The fee comes at
the end. So now I've finally finished, and now that I've finished
I'm saying you know what, don't owe me the money, I am
giving you the gift of my labor. So that type of a
case that is a gift I've given her that's worth a שווה
פרוטה. Shaveh Perutah. רבנן סברי Rabanan Savri and the Rabbis hold ישנה
לשכירות מתחילה ועד סוף. Yeshna Lis'chirus Misatchala V'ad Sof. No, you it
it's a debt that's been accruing. So therefore it's just money that
she owes you, and therefore you can't be מקדש במלווה. Mekadesh B'milveh.
So that's another way of explaining the debate. ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'is Teima,
if you want you could say דכולי עלמא ישנה לשכירות מתחילה ועד
סוף. Dechulei Alma Yeshna Lis'chirus Misatchala V'ad Sof. Everybody says from beginning
to end. Okay, so it is a debt, and if it's a
debt then what's the debate about? הכא במקדש במלווה קמיפלגי. Hacha B'mikadesh
B'milveh Kamiflagi. Maybe the debate is can you marry a woman with
money she owes
you. רבי מאיר סבר מקדש במלווה מקודשת ורבנן סברי מקדש במלווה אינה
מקודשת. Rebbi Meir Savar Mikadesh B'milveh Mikudeshes V'rabanan Savri Mikadesh B'milveh Eina
Mikudeshes. Okay, we have a lot of that in קידושין. Kiddushin.
הני בני מערבא Hani Bnei Ma'arava say, right, right,
right.
Now let's try to do one more thing. רבא אמר, Rava Amar,
רבא Rava said, דכולי עלמא ישנה
לשכירות מתחילה ועד סוף. Dechulei Alma Yeshna Lis'chirus Misatchala V'ad Sof. Everybody
would say from beginning to end. דכולי עלמא מקדש במלווה אינה מקודשת.
Dechulei Alma Mikadesh B'milveh Eina Mikudeshes. And the מלווה Milveh doesn't work.
ודכולי עלמא אינו אומן קונה בשבח כלי. U'dechulei Alma Eino Uman Koneh
B'shvach Kli. You can't be מקדש Mekadesh her with the מלווה. Milveh.
You can't be מקדש Mekadesh her with the gift of your labor.
You can't be מקדש Mekadesh her with your value that you own
in the improved gold because your אומן Uman is not קונה בשבח
כלי. Koneh B'shvach Kli. So what what are you being מקדש Mekadesh
her with according to רבי מאיר? Rebbi Meir? אלא הכא במאי עסקינן
כגון שהוסיף לה נופך משלו. Ela Hacha B'mai Askinan Kegon Shehosif Lah
Nofech Mishelo. That basically you basically She said, you know, the fee
of a hundred dollars to make it into a type of a
bracelet, and then what you did is you, because you loved her
so much, you made an extra little engravement, an extra little, you
know, improvement that normally would not be part of the fee. Okay,
and that was your gift to her. That was not something that
was agreed upon. Okay. Yes. Yes.
Yes, so let's take a look.
What?
Can she marry herself?
Right, with
my own little personal special touch. So רבי מאיר סבר, Rebbi Meir
savar, so רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir holds מלוה ופרוטה דעתה אפרוטה, milve
u'pruta daata a'pruta, that it's basically, you know, there's a debt. So
he asked me to do X. I did X plus a little
extra. So therefore now I give it to her. So somebody's even
though I'm giving her something worth basically being מוחל mochel a hundred
dollar debt that she owes me. The fact that I'm being מוחל
mochel a hundred dollar debt but I'm also giving something concrete, you
know, right now, so a person is not necessarily just focus—people are
not totally, you know, rational, like to say totally cynical, like they
say
the difference between a cynic who knows the price of everything and
the value of nothing. So people don't just look at the dollar
cost of something. Even though you're being מוחל mochel a hundred dollar
debt, there's something concrete that you're giving right now and something personal,
well here it's personal but רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir would say even
if it's פרוטה pruta out of פרוטה. pruta. A man says to
a woman, "I am מקדש mekadesh you. I'm מוחל mochel a hundred
dollars you owe me and here's a פרוטה pruta and I'm מקדש
mekadesh you." It's not too much of personal about a פרוטה. pruta.
Here it's personal. But nevertheless the fact that it's present and physical
and concrete, a person actually
can—the מלוה milve doesn't overshadow that. And they can focus on the
פרוטה pruta and the פרוטה pruta can be the object of the
קידושין. kiddushin. Okay, דעתה אפרוטה. daata a'pruta. ורבנן סברי מלוה ופרוטה דעתה
אמלוה, V'rabbanan savri milve u'pruta daata a'milve, and the מלוה milve overshadows
it and therefore fundamentally the person is only thinking about that as
what they're receiving and a מלוה milve is not something that you
could be מקדש mekadesh with. ובפלוגתא דהני תנאי, U've-plugta d'hanei tanna-ei, and
it's the same as the debate of the following
תנאי. tanna-ei. דתניא, D'tanya, בשכר שעשיתי עמך, bischar she'asiti imach, if somebody
says,
"I will marry you, you know, I worked on your car." You
go to the mechanic and the mechanic says, "You know what? You
owe me a thousand dollars for the work on the car, but
tell you what, forget about what I owe you and marry me
with that, with the fee that you owe me." With the work
that I've already done.
With the new radiator? With the work that I've already done for
you.
אינה מקודשת. Eina mekudeshet. That's not good. You know why? Because that's
מקדש במלוה. mekadesh be-milve. The debt was already incurred. בשכר שאעשה עמך—or
Bischar she'e'eseh imach עמך imach I guess—if the person said, "You know
what? I'll do the work on your radiator but for the work
I will do for you, you'll marry me." Okay, so what's the
story? So מקודשת. mekudeshet. That does work. Okay? That's like the רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir and the gold, we'll see what that's about. רבי
נתן אומר בשכר שאעשה עמך אינה מקודשת וכל שכן בשכר שעשיתי עמך.
Rebbi Natan omer bischar she'e'eseh imach eina mekudeshet v'chol shekein bischar she'asiti
imach. Neither way works, okay? Whether it's the past debt or work
you're going to do. רבי יהודה הנשיא אומר אמש אמרו בין בשכר
שעשיתי עמך בין בשכר שאעשה עמך אינה מקודשת. Rebbi Yehuda HaNasi omer
emesh amru bein bischar she'asiti imach bein bischar she'e'eseh imach eina mekudeshet.
Neither way works, which is what
רבי נתן Rebbi Natan says. אבל אם הוסיף לה נופך משלו מקודשת.
Aval im hosif lah nofach mishelo mekudeshet. That works. So what's the
debate?
So the גמרא Gemara says... what?
He can't say, "Oh look I added a little something, we're engaged
now."
No no no.
He would have to say,
"I am marrying you with what I've added." Right.
And
she would have to agree. Okay, now. So בין תנא קמא לרבי
נתן, bein tanna kamma l'Rebbi Natan,
does it work when it says the work that I will do
for you? So איכא בינייהו שכירות. ika beinaihu sechiros. That's the question
about שכירות, sechiros, if ישנה לשכירות מתחילה ועד סוף, yeshna l'sechiros mitchila
v'ad sof, right? Or you could say whether it's אומן קונה בשבח
כלי. uman koneh b'shevach kli. All right. But you know,
if ישנה לשכירות מתחילה ועד סוף, yeshna l'sechiros mitchila v'ad sof, then
even if it's work I'm gonna do for you, by the time
the work is done, it's a debt and it's still מקדש במלוה.
mekadesh be-milve. If אינה לשכירות אלא לבסוף, eina l'sechiros ela l'sof, then
the obligation only comes at the end and then you're giving the
gift of your labor. Okay? So that would be that. Or maybe
it's אומן קונה בשבח כלי. uman koneh b'shevach kli. And בין רבי
לרבי נתן, bein Rebbi l'Rabbi Natan, now what's the issue about the
idea that everybody agrees that it doesn't work? But there's a debate
of if you add your own little extra thing that you throw
in? So according to that, רבי נתן, רבי יהודה הנשיא—בין רבי נתן
לרבי יהודה הנשיא איכא בינייהו מלוה ופרוטה. Rebbi Natan, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi—bein
Rabbi Natan l'Rebbi Yehuda HaNasi ika beinaihu milve u'pruta. The case about
a מלוה ופרוטה, milve u'pruta, whether when you throw in that extra
little thing is that enough to be מקדש mekadesh even though that
wasn't sort of like the agreed upon—what was agreed upon? Okay? So
we'll end with this here. Unfortunately, we're still a little bit behind,
but the next thing turns us real—is going to turn us back.
This was real בבא קמא Bava Kamma stuff because it was about
like a change and owning the improvement you've created through your change.
Now the גמרא's Gemara going to turn back to the real point
of the משנה, mishna, which is the case of מזיק. mazik. And
under what circumstances are you liable if you mess up on a
job that you've done, can you be treated as a מזיק mazik
and have to pay for the damage.
Okay. Let's finish גמרא Gemara couple huge תוספות. Tosafots.
Yes, I think tomorrow we'll catch up. Okay?
There's an old Archie comic that where Jughead is mowing lawn
and Archie
comes over and says, "What are you doing? I thought you were
supposed to be cleaning the attic." And he says, "I am cleaning
the attic. But to clean the attic, I have to move the
trunk. To move the trunk, I have to move the bicycle. The
bicycle is in the garage. To move the bicycle, I have to
move the lawnmower. The lawnmower won't start, so I have to go
get gas for the lawnmower so I can move the lawnmower so
I can move the bicycle so I can move the trunk so
I can clean the attic." That's how I feel about this גמרא.
Gemara. Right now we're doing the things we need to do to
get to the things we need to do. דף פ''א עמוד ב',
daf pei aleph amud bet, top of the page. אמר רב אסי.
Amar Rav Assi. Rav Assi says המאבד קרדומו של חברו, hame'abed kardumo
shel chaveiro, one who loses his friend's ax, אמר ליה, amar lei,
says to him הא קרדומך וזיל, ha kardumach v'zil, "Here is your
ax and go." And the גמרא Gemara asks כמאן? keman? Like who
is this like? לימא רבי מאיר היא? leima Rabbi Meir hi? Let
us say it is like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, דדאין דינא דגרמי,
d'da'in dina d'garmi, who judges the laws of indirect damage.